<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://docs.mecsimcalc.com/blog</id>
    <title>MecSimCalc Docs Blog</title>
    <updated>2022-08-05T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://docs.mecsimcalc.com/blog"/>
    <subtitle>MecSimCalc Docs Blog</subtitle>
    <icon>https://docs.mecsimcalc.com/img/favicon.ico</icon>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Johns Apps]]></title>
        <id>Johns-apps</id>
        <link href="https://docs.mecsimcalc.com/blog/Johns-apps"/>
        <updated>2022-08-05T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[The following blogposts were written by John Yu for various apps he had created on MecSimCalc.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The following blogposts were written by John Yu for various apps he had created on MecSimCalc. </p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="pairwise-testing-generator"><strong>Pairwise Testing Generator</strong><a class="hash-link" href="#pairwise-testing-generator" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>This blog post is dedicated to the <a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/8809236/pairwise_testing_generator" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pairwise Testing Generator</a> app created by John Yu.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="about-the-pairwise-testing-generator"><strong><em>About the Pairwise Testing Generator</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#about-the-pairwise-testing-generator" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>The pairwise testing generator is an app that can generate a set of test cases with up to 5
independent variables. The app uses a technique called Taguchi Orthogonal Arrays such that
every pairing of variables appears in at least one test case. This method is significantly more
powerful and more efficient compared to brute-force testing. You can get full testing coverage
of your program using significantly less test cases. This can save you a lot of time and a lot of
money depending on the size of your program.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="why-i-made-this-app"><strong><em>Why I made this app</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#why-i-made-this-app" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Software testing is a critical step in the software development lifecycle. There are countless
opportunities for mistakes and defects to come up at any point in the development of software.
Fixing code is equally as important as creating code. Finding these bugs early in the
development lifecycle will help to mitigate issues that come up later. The hard part of testing
code is generating test cases. Full code coverage often comes with a huge set of test cases
which is expensive and time consuming. A small set of test cases is cost effective but lacks code
coverage. I made this app to help software engineers generate test cases that can provide
adequate code coverage in a reasonable amount of test cases. This saves you a lot of time and
money and improves the quality of your code.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="simple-linear-regression-and-discrete-probability-distribution"><strong>Simple Linear Regression and Discrete Probability Distribution</strong><a class="hash-link" href="#simple-linear-regression-and-discrete-probability-distribution" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>This blog post is dedicated to the <a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/3625435/simple_linear_regression" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Simple Linear Regression</a> and <a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/8359657/visualizing_discrete_probability_distributions" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Visualizing Discrete Probability Distributions</a> apps created by John Yu.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="about-the-simple-linear-regression-and-the-discrete-probability-distribution-app"><strong><em>About the Simple Linear Regression and the Discrete Probability Distribution App</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#about-the-simple-linear-regression-and-the-discrete-probability-distribution-app" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>The simple linear regression app can generate a regression line from your set of data points.
The app is intended to be a helpful tool for Statistics students to understand how the linear
regression line is calculated. There are no statistical libraries used in the calculation of the
regression line. All calculations are done using equations from my statistics textbook. The app
will calculate the regression line as well as show you how the calculation is performed. In
statistics, there are many formulas that can calculate a regression line. This app uses the
simplest equation to help students gain a better understanding of how the regression line is
calculated.</p><p>The Discrete Probability Distribution app can visualize common probability distributions in
Statistics. This app is intended to be a helpful tool for students taking Statistics to understand
how these probability distributions work. The user can play around with the parameters of the
distributions defined in the app inputs to understand how these parameters impact the graph.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="truth-table-generator"><strong>Truth Table Generator</strong><a class="hash-link" href="#truth-table-generator" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>This blog post is dedicated to the <a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/4669459/truth_table_generator" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Truth Table Generator</a> app created by John Yu.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="about-the-truth-table-generator-app"><strong><em>About the Truth Table Generator App</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#about-the-truth-table-generator-app" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>The truth table generator is an app that can generate a truth table by defining a logical
expression. You can define a logic expression simply by typing it into the app inputs. The app
will evaluate your expression with each possible combination of inputs and return the expected
output. This app is intended to be used by students taking a digital logic class who need to
quickly generate a truth table. Sometimes a logic expression may be very complicated to
evaluate by hand. This app can generate a truth table with any expression no matter how
complicated it is. Students will find this app by helpful for verifying your truth table. The app
has been tested multiple times to ensure that the expected outputs are correct.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>John Yu</name>
        </author>
        <category label="MecSimCalc" term="MecSimCalc"/>
        <category label="Computer Science" term="Computer Science"/>
        <category label="Engineering" term="Engineering"/>
        <category label="Math" term="Math"/>
        <category label="Statistics" term="Statistics"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Useful Webtools]]></title>
        <id>websiteplanet-2022</id>
        <link href="https://docs.mecsimcalc.com/blog/websiteplanet-2022"/>
        <updated>2022-08-03T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blogpost is dedicated to webtools developed by WebsitePlanet. You can visit all of their webtools at WebsitePlanet.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This blogpost is dedicated to webtools developed by WebsitePlanet. You can visit all of their webtools at <a href="https://www.websiteplanet.com/webtools/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">WebsitePlanet</a>.</p><table><thead><tr><th>App</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><a href="https://www.websiteplanet.com/webtools/jscssminifier/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">JS and CSS Minifier</a></td><td>This tool makes your website run faster and take up less data by "minifying" the JavaScript and CSS code.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://www.websiteplanet.com/webtools/unminify-js/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">JS and CSS Unminifier</a></td><td>This tool unminifies JavaScript and CSS code to be more readable for users.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://www.websiteplanet.com/webtools/imagecompressor/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Image Compressor</a></td><td>This tool compresses PNG/JPG images to up to 80% of it's original size, lowering it's data size.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://www.websiteplanet.com/webtools/free-qr-code-generator/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">QR Code Generator</a></td><td>This tool creates a custom, high-resolution QR code that directs users to websites, emails, social media sites and more.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://www.websiteplanet.com/webtools/favicon-generator/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Favicon Generator</a></td><td>This tool automatically resizes an image to a favicon in PNG format.</td></tr></tbody></table>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Daren Trinh</name>
            <uri>https://www.linkedin.com/in/daren-trinh-3816b0187/</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[MecSimCalc Build-A-Thon (July 9th - July 16th, 2022) Winners]]></title>
        <id>Comp07092022-Winners</id>
        <link href="https://docs.mecsimcalc.com/blog/Comp07092022-Winners"/>
        <updated>2022-07-18T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[MecSimCalc had it's first ever hackathon in July 2022. This competition sponsored by 1984 Ventures, was aimed to increase the number of users and showcase the versatility of the platform. Users would create an app on the MecSimCalc website, tag it as "Comp07092022" and publish it for a chance to win up $500. $400 would be given to the app with the highest score and $100 would be given to the most viewed app. However, since we had received so many high quality submissions, three additional bonus prizes were given out to apps that had not won but were innovative uses of the platform. Throughout the competition there were 77 sign-ups and 13 submissions. This blog post is dedicated to the top 5 scoring apps from MecSimCalc's July 9th - July 16th, 2022 Build-A-Thon. To view all apps submitted during the competition, look for the tag "Comp07092022" on the MecSimCalc Explore page.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>MecSimCalc had it's first ever hackathon in July 2022. This competition sponsored by 1984 Ventures, was aimed to increase the number of users and showcase the versatility of the platform. Users would create an app on the MecSimCalc website, tag it as "Comp07092022" and publish it for a chance to win up $500. $400 would be given to the app with the highest score and $100 would be given to the most viewed app. However, since we had received so many high quality submissions, three additional bonus prizes were given out to apps that had not won but were innovative uses of the platform. Throughout the competition there were 77 sign-ups and 13 submissions. This blog post is dedicated to the top 5 scoring apps from MecSimCalc's July 9th - July 16th, 2022 Build-A-Thon. To view all apps submitted during the competition, look for the tag "Comp07092022" on the MecSimCalc Explore page.</p><table><thead><tr><th>App</th><th>Author(s)</th><th>Win</th><th>Prize</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/6179554/%F0%9D%90%A2_%F0%9D%90%8C_%F0%9D%90%9E_%F0%9D%90%9D_%F0%9D%90%A2_%F0%9D%90%9C_high_tech_accessible_care_%F0%9D%90%85_%F0%9D%90%A8_%F0%9D%90%AB_%F0%9D%90%80_%F0%9D%90%A5_%F0%9D%90%A5" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">iMedic</a></td><td>Zarik Khan, Dorsa Rohani, Videet Mehta</td><td>Grand Prize Winner (Highest score)</td><td>$400 CAD</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/1569496/javelin_power_saver_cuts_your_electricity_bill_smartly" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Javelin Power Saver</a></td><td>Chetan Tyagi</td><td>Most viewed app</td><td>$100 CAD</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/5416553/grids_for_artists" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Grids for artists</a></td><td>Camilo Andrés Rojas Hernández</td><td>Innovative use of MecSimCalc</td><td>$100 CAD</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/5317027/2_d_heat_equation_visualizer" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">2D Heat Equation Visualizer</a></td><td>Jasper Eitzen</td><td>Innovative use of MecSimCalc</td><td>$100 CAD</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/4663263/lyme_ml" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">LymeML</a></td><td>Soham Jain</td><td>Innovative use of MecSimCalc</td><td>$100 CAD</td></tr></tbody></table><hr><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="imedic"><strong><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/6179554/%F0%9D%90%A2_%F0%9D%90%8C_%F0%9D%90%9E_%F0%9D%90%9D_%F0%9D%90%A2_%F0%9D%90%9C_high_tech_accessible_care_%F0%9D%90%85_%F0%9D%90%A8_%F0%9D%90%AB_%F0%9D%90%80_%F0%9D%90%A5_%F0%9D%90%A5" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">iMedic</a></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#imedic" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><hr><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="bio-dorsa-rohani"><strong><em>Bio: Dorsa Rohani</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#bio-dorsa-rohani" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Dorsa Rohani is a current high school student at Pierre Elliott Trudeau High School in Ontario, Canada. From electrical and computer engineering to healthcare and medicine, Dorsa is passionate about the intersection between technology and healthcare. In creating iMedic, Dorsa aimed to define the patient experience, and to address the ongoing predicament surrounding the chronic lack of access to efficient and accurate medical diagnosis. Indeed, across the continuum of care, the execution of ethical medical examination is of high precedence. In her spare time, she enjoys challenging herself, as well as performing the cello with her local string orchestra. </p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="bio-videet-mehta"><strong><em>Bio: Videet Mehta</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#bio-videet-mehta" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Videet Mehta is a rising Junior at Dulles High School in Sugar Land Texas. He is passionate about both medicine and technology. For the last four years, he has built robots that have been placed at the top of the First Tech Challenge state and world championships. He also does competitive programming and is currently in the silver division of the USACO competition. He learned python and ML just over a year ago. And since then, he has created many medically related machine learning projects. Additionally, he is the co-founder of two ed-tech companies: Project SUCCEED (<a href="https://projectsucceed.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">projectsucceed.org</a>) and Xceleration (<a href="https://xceleration.org/dl/welcome" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">xceleration.org</a>). </p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="bio-zarik-khan"><strong><em>Bio: Zarik Khan</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#bio-zarik-khan" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Hi, I'm Zarik Khan and I'm a rising junior at Dulles High School. I'm passionate about machine learning, bioinformatics, web development, biomedical engineering, and app development. I worked with Videet and Dorsa to create iMedic to contribute to the distribution of medical technology in areas around the world that lack accessible access. Our project was made to detect some of the fatal causes of death in these areas to provide people a way to monitor their health and take necessary action quickly. MecsimCalc allowed us to integrate our python code into an easy, aesthetic, and secure front-end system. We hope to innovate on our current project by improving the accuracy of our calculations, expanding our app's reach, and developing new features. </p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="about-imedic"><strong><em>About iMedic</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#about-imedic" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>From the detection of infectious, cancerous, and cardiovascular diseases using a variety of means; to academic tools such as 3D computations of Chaos Theory, iMedic is a multipurpose platform that uses ML, AI, libraries, and big data. As an app created for Third World countries &amp; rural areas, it is for individuals who do not have access to medical support nor fast and efficient examination. iMedic is designed to be used frequently to evaluate one's risks for the most common medical conditions, and to provide users with knowledge of their current health. In addition, iMedic includes cutting-edge tools for research. By including a chaos calculator—that computes &amp; graphs chaotic systems such as the Lorenz Attractor &amp; Logistic Map with yielded data via input—iMedic has many applications to fields extending far beyond medicine, such as data science, math, and CS as well.</p><hr><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="javelin-power-saver"><strong><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/1569496/javelin_power_saver_cuts_your_electricity_bill_smartly" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Javelin Power Saver</a></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#javelin-power-saver" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><hr><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="bio-chetan-tyagi"><strong><em>Bio: Chetan Tyagi</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#bio-chetan-tyagi" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>I am Chetan Tyagi, who will be joining University of Alberta for the undergraduate in Computing Science this fall, and is very keen to learn new things about the subject and keep up to date with the latest technologies.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="about-javelin-power-saver"><strong><em>About Javelin Power Saver</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#about-javelin-power-saver" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>My app is called "Javelin Power Saver". As the name suggests, this application aims to conserve your energy, and therefore cut your bill. With the help of this easy-to-use app, you will be able to
-calculate the power your appliances uses per month -the total money you spend on them in a month
-compare yourself with the electricity bill of an average citizen
-compare your appliances with popular products in the same range</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="why-i-made-this-app"><strong><em>Why I made this app</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#why-i-made-this-app" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>As per a report by World Economic Forum, the end use efficiency of electricity in residential environment in USA is a mere 65%, signifying the level of wastage of energy. The waste of electricity ends up in increasing the costs for the user, while also making a carbon footprint on the environment. The application will focus on conserving electricity. The target users of this application will be all the people who use electricity in their homes.</p><p>A big proportion of people in both urban and rural areas use electrical appliances and pay the electricity bill. It is common to look at the bill and thinking how the cost can be reduced. But as there is no way of accurately understanding how, we guess on different appliances, which makes the process harder. This application solves this. Also, before getting a new electrical appliance, we will be able to estimate the total power consumption, estimate total costs, compare with average households, and recommend how the user can make the combination of electrical appliances more efficient.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="my-experience-with-mecsimcalc"><strong><em>My experience with MecSimCalc</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#my-experience-with-mecsimcalc" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Compared from my previous experiences of creating web-apps, making apps here is much easier than anywhere else I have seen on the internet. It is completely free, encouraging both beginners and professionals to create apps without any hindrance. Overall, this is a great website to work on and I will recommend it to everyone interested in creating apps using Python.</p><hr><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="grids-for-artists"><strong><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/5416553/grids_for_artists" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Grids for artists</a></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#grids-for-artists" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><hr><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="bio-camilo-andrés-rojas-hernández"><strong><em>Bio: Camilo Andrés Rojas Hernández</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#bio-camilo-andrés-rojas-hernández" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>I am Camilo Andrés Rojas Hernández, mathematics student at the Universidad Nacional de Colombia Medellin, since about 6 years ago I have learned on my own the development in python, its libraries and frameworks, something that identifies me is self-taught learning because over the years I have developed both soft skills and technical skills in the language, I am very motivated by programming and learning things every day.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="about-grids-for-artists"><strong><em>About Grids for artists</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#about-grids-for-artists" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>I made this application because since my sister studies plastic arts, sometimes she has problems when it comes to making guide grids for her canvases, so I wanted to satisfy that need she had using python and the MecSimCalc tool, it is very easy to use, plus it has the main libraries, such as machine learning and image processing, in this case with Pillow, the input and output of data is very comfortable, anyone can share and create applications in record time. Awesome!</p><hr><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="2d-heat-equation-visualizer"><strong><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/5317027/2_d_heat_equation_visualizer" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">2D Heat Equation Visualizer</a></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#2d-heat-equation-visualizer" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><hr><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="bio-jasper-eitzen-and-about-2d-heat-equation-visualizer"><strong><em>Bio: Jasper Eitzen and About 2D Heat Equation Visualizer</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#bio-jasper-eitzen-and-about-2d-heat-equation-visualizer" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>My name is Jasper Eitzen, I’m currently a graduate student at the University of Alberta, pursuing a Master of Science in Mechanical Engineering. The work I do for my thesis mostly consists of lab experiments, although I do have experience using Python to analyse experimental data as well as some programming experience from my undergrad and graduate studies. I came up with the idea for 2D Heat Equation Visualizer from having written some simple numerical solvers in the past and seeing that MecSimCalc could provide a convenient way to get inputs from the user. I thought that the results of such an app could look quite interesting since I’ve done similar projects in the past, and I always found it cool to set up an initial condition and see how it evolves over time based on math and physics. With contour plots as outputs, users can play around with the app’s inputs to try and get unique results. I needed quite a few inputs and the input page on MecSimCalc was very useful in letting me lay them all out and provide explanations so that the user could pick values that provide good results. As someone with no experience in web development, I wouldn’t have been able to make something like this app without the interface that MecSimCalc provided.</p><hr><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="lymeml"><strong><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/4663263/lyme_ml" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">LymeML</a></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#lymeml" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><hr><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="bio-soham-jain"><strong><em>Bio: Soham Jain</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#bio-soham-jain" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Soham Jain is currently a sophomore with a passion for machine learning at Thomas Jefferson High School for Science and Technology, a prestigious high school that is ranked #1 in the United States. He works as a Machine Learning Engineer for a local start-up company called Vytal, where he assists in creating novel ML algorithms for fast and comprehensive neurologic and cardiac assessment through smartphone-based applications. In the past, he has worked closely with machine learning models using classification techniques to diagnose medical conditions, such as Malaria and Lyme disease. He has also won several awards from hackathons in the past through developing contemporary algorithms and deploying applications to assist with effective clinical diagnoses. As a technology specialist on the executive committee for his school's Student Government Association, Soham has used his experience in computer science to assist the student body with leading events and initiatives. Soham is also passionate about competition math, as he has competed in numerous national-level contests such as AIME, AMC 10, and MathCounts. Outside of school, Soham likes to tutor other students, play the piano, spend time with friends, and listen to music.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="about-lymeml"><strong><em>About LymeML</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#about-lymeml" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>LymeML is an application built on MecSimCalc that uses novel machine learning algorithms to diagnose Lyme disease, a prevalent issue in numerous countries around the world. Research suggests that 14% of the world's population is currently affected or has been affected in the past with Lyme disease, contributing to the significance of this issue. Contemporary methods to diagnose this disease require a blood test. with lab reports anticipated to arrive three or four weeks after the patient seeks medical attention. However, waiting several days to receive a diagnosis allows symptoms to worsen, causing detrimental and irreversible damage to the brain or heart. Soham Jain, a current high school sophomore in the United States and Machine Learning Engineer at a local startup company, noticed that this issue can be resolved through creating a machine learning algorithm that sends an effective and immediate result to the user through image classification and a self-check symptoms diagnosis. This app implements convolutional neural networks (CNNs) and Python libraries such as NumPy and TensorFlow to accurately diagnose Lyme disease. Implementing this app will help several individuals living in remote areas to expedite the process of receiving a medical diagnosis, and differentiate their symptoms/rashes from those of other diseases. With the help of machine learning and MecSimCalc for making this app available to others, countless individuals will receive an instant diagnosis of Lyme disease and can treat their symptoms faster.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="my-experience-with-mecsimcalc-1"><strong><em>My experience with MecSimCalc</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#my-experience-with-mecsimcalc-1" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>With the help of MecSimCalc, LymeML will continue on its mission to aid countless more individuals living in remote areas to receive an instant diagnosis for Lyme disease, and can treat their symptoms more efficiently. Through featuring LymeML as a winner for this hackathon, the opportunities for telemedicine and machine learning algorithms in the future has opened, and soon more accurate and immediate models will be created to diagnose several diseases. Creating the LymeML app through MecSimCalc was very straightforward and many Python libraries were accessible. The documentation and app analytics were also available, making my experience with this website more professional and enjoyable.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Daren Trinh</name>
            <uri>https://www.linkedin.com/in/daren-trinh-3816b0187/</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="MecSimCalc" term="MecSimCalc"/>
        <category label="Comp07092022" term="Comp07092022"/>
        <category label="hackathon" term="hackathon"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Masonry Calculators]]></title>
        <id>masonry-calculators-2022</id>
        <link href="https://docs.mecsimcalc.com/blog/masonry-calculators-2022"/>
        <updated>2022-07-18T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Masonry is the building of structures from individual units, which are often laid in and bound together by mortar.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p><strong>Masonry</strong> is the building of structures from individual units, which are often laid in and bound together by mortar.</p></blockquote><p><img loading="lazy" alt="masonry" src="/assets/images/masonry-134ec92294f58c2911b22e497dd3a744.jpeg" width="1000" height="449" class="img_ev3q"></p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="authors">Authors<a class="hash-link" href="#authors" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p><strong>Dr. Mark D. Hagel</strong> is the Executive Director of Alberta Masonry Council and has kindly made his masonry calculators available on MecSimCalc.
Mark holds a Bachelor of Science in Actuarial Science and Applied Mathematics, a Bachelor of Science in Civil Engineering, and a Doctor of Philosophy in Civil Engineering all from the University of Calgary. Mark’s fields of expertise include thermal and hygrothermal modeling of building systems, corrosion modeling, Life Cycle Cost Analysis, structural analysis and design, and the durability of building components. In 2018 Mark served on the National Research Council of Canada’s (NRC) working group that developed the Guideline on Design for Durability of the Building Envelope.</p><p><strong>John Yu</strong> is a university researcher who converted Dr. Hagel's excel files into MecSimCalc apps.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="thermal-calculation-apps">Thermal calculation apps<a class="hash-link" href="#thermal-calculation-apps" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><table><thead><tr><th>Thermal calculation app</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/6855626/bvcu_thermal_catalog_app" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">BVCU Thermal Catalog App</a></td><td>An App that calculates the clear field (Uo) and linear transmittance (psi) values for foundation, floor, parapet corner and window/doors for Brick Veneer Concrete Block Unit (BVCU) wall systems for any value of exterior insulation. These values are needed to thermal bridging calculations to comply with the National Energy Code for Buildings (NECB).</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/1652032/bvws_thermal_catalog_app" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">BVWS Thermal Catalog App</a></td><td>An App that calculates the clear field Uo and linear transmittance values for foundation, floor, parapet corner and window/doors for Brick Veneer Concrete Block Unit (BVCU) wall systems for any value of exterior insulation. These values are needed to thermal bridging calculations to comply with the National Energy Code for Buildings (NECB).</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/6727343/bvss_thermal_catalog_app" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">BVSS Thermal Catalog App</a></td><td>An App that calculates the clear field Uo and linear transmittance values for foundation, floor, parapet corner and window/doors for Brick Veneer Steel Stud (BVSS) wall systems for any value of exterior insulation. These values are needed to thermal bridging calculations to comply with the National Energy Code for Buildings (NECB).</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/7431858/thermal_bridging_assembly_calculation" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Thermal Bridging Assembly Calculation</a></td><td>An App based on the BC hydro/Fortis/Powersmart “Enhanced Thermal Performance Spreadsheet”. The app calculates the impact on the clear field of a wall elevation from the thermal bridging effects of linear transmittances (foundation, floor, roof, corner, window/doors) and point transmittances (signage, etc.)</td></tr></tbody></table><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="life-cycle-cost-analysis-apps">Life cycle cost analysis apps<a class="hash-link" href="#life-cycle-cost-analysis-apps" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><table><thead><tr><th>Life cycle cost analysis app</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/3605070/cladding_life_cost_comparison" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Cladding Life Cost Comparison</a></td><td>An App that calculates the cost of up to three different cladding systems for a given building service life, inflation rate and discount rate using Life Cycle Cost Analysis (LCCA).</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/8921970/building_envelope_life_cost_comparison_calculator" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Building Envelope Life Cost Comparison Calculator</a></td><td>An App that calculates the cost of up to three different cladding AND roofing systems for a given building service life, inflation rate and discount rate using Life Cycle Cost Analysis (LCCA).</td></tr></tbody></table><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="carbon-sequestration-apps">Carbon sequestration apps<a class="hash-link" href="#carbon-sequestration-apps" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><table><thead><tr><th>Carbon sequestration app</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/9771381/cmu_block_wall_carbon_calculator" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">CMU Block Wall Carbon Calculator</a></td><td>An App to calculate the amount of carbon sequestered when constructing with concrete block masonry.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/2907334/brick_veneer_carbon_calculator" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Brick Veneer Carbon Calculator</a></td><td>An App to calculate the amount of carbon sequestered when constructing with clay brick veneer.</td></tr></tbody></table>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Mark Hagel</name>
        </author>
        <author>
            <name>John Yu</name>
        </author>
        <category label="Calculators" term="Calculators"/>
        <category label="Civil Engineering" term="Civil Engineering"/>
        <category label="Engineering" term="Engineering"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Circuit Analysis Calculators]]></title>
        <id>electrical-calculators-2022</id>
        <link href="https://docs.mecsimcalc.com/blog/electrical-calculators-2022"/>
        <updated>2022-06-20T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog post is dedicated to circuit analysis calculators created for MecSimCalc.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This blog post is dedicated to circuit analysis calculators created for MecSimCalc.</p><table><thead><tr><th>App</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/2144200/voltage_divider_calculator" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Voltage Divider Calculator</a></td><td>This is an app for a voltage divider circuit. The user first inputs the input voltage (V), and the values of two resistors (Ω, kΩ, MΩ). Using the inputs and the voltage divider equation, the output voltage (V) measured across resistor 2 is returned.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/9979869/current_divider_calculator" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Current Divider Calculator</a></td><td>This is an app for a current divider circuit. The user inputs an input voltage (V) and the values of up to 5 resistors (Ω) in parallel. After finding the total current, the calculator uses the current divider equation to generate a table showing the various current (A) flowing through each resistor.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/8349728/op_amp_gain_and_output_voltage_calculator" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Op-Amp Gain and Output Voltage Calculator</a></td><td>Operational amplifiers are an active circuit component commonly used in various circuits. This app uses an op-amp in two common configurations, an inverting and non-inverting amplifier. The user selects which configuration they are using, the value of the input resistor (Ω, kΩ, MΩ), the feedback resistor (Ω, kΩ, MΩ) and the input voltage (V). Depending on the circuit chosen, a gain and the corresponding output voltage is calculated and displayed as well as an image of the circuit schematic.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/8934998/parallel_resistance_calculator" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Parallel Resistance Calculator</a></td><td>This app calculates the equivalent resistance of a circuit containing resistors in parallel. The user inputs up to 8 resistors (Ω) and using the parallel resistance equation, an equivalent resistance for the circuit is returned.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/7370385/resistor_color_code_calculator" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Resistor Color Code Calculator (4 Band)</a></td><td>This app decodes the value of a 4 band axial lead resistor. The user selects 4 colors (left to right), and the corresponding resistance value and tolerance is given.</td></tr></tbody></table>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Daren Trinh</name>
            <uri>https://www.linkedin.com/in/daren-trinh-3816b0187/</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="Calculators" term="Calculators"/>
        <category label="Electrical Engineering" term="Electrical Engineering"/>
        <category label="Engineering" term="Engineering"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pharmacy Tools]]></title>
        <id>pharmacy-tools-2022</id>
        <link href="https://docs.mecsimcalc.com/blog/pharmacy-tools-2022"/>
        <updated>2022-06-19T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[At MecSimCalc, our hope is to bring industries still using spreadsheets and PDFs online. With MecSimCalc, it is now possible to share tools easier and run calculations faster than ever before.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At MecSimCalc, our hope is to bring industries still using spreadsheets and PDFs online. With MecSimCalc, it is now possible to share tools easier and run calculations faster than ever before.</p><p>This blog post is dedicated to Pharmacy tools that we have converted from PDF files into interactive online tools.</p><table><thead><tr><th>Tool</th><th>Source</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/0233855/diabetes_risk" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Diabetes Risk</a></td><td><a href="https://health.canada.ca/apps/canrisk-standalone/pdf/canrisk-en.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Health Canada</a></td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/8086574/body_surface_area_bsa" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Body Surface Area (BSA)</a></td><td><a href="https://www.pharmacists.ca/cpha-ca/assets/File/education-practice-resources/CalcAndDosing_EN_26Feb08.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pharmacists.ca</a></td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/5081549/body_surface_area_in_infants_children_or_adults" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Body Surface Area in Infants, Children or Adults</a></td><td><a href="https://www.pharmacists.ca/cpha-ca/assets/File/education-practice-resources/CalcAndDosing_EN_26Feb08.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pharmacists.ca</a></td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/5519816/ideal_body_weight_ibw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Ideal Body Weight (IBW)</a></td><td><a href="https://www.pharmacists.ca/cpha-ca/assets/File/education-practice-resources/CalcAndDosing_EN_26Feb08.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pharmacists.ca</a></td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/7850429/adjusted_body_weight_abw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Adjusted Body Weight (ABW)</a></td><td><a href="https://www.pharmacists.ca/cpha-ca/assets/File/education-practice-resources/CalcAndDosing_EN_26Feb08.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pharmacists.ca</a></td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/8292339/creatinine_clearance_cl_cr" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Creatinine Clearance (ClCr)</a></td><td><a href="https://www.pharmacists.ca/cpha-ca/assets/File/education-practice-resources/CalcAndDosing_EN_26Feb08.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pharmacists.ca</a></td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/9081445/framingham_risk_score_frs" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Framingham Risk Score (FRS)</a></td><td><a href="https://ccs.ca/app/uploads/2020/12/FRS_eng_2017_fnl_greyscale.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Canadian Cardiovascular Society</a></td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/0114458/ukpds_cardiac_risk_calculator" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">UKPDS Cardiac Risk Calculator</a></td><td><a href="https://www.mdapp.co/ukpds-cardiac-risk-calculator-215/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MDApp</a></td></tr></tbody></table>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Weichen Qiu</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/w3ichen</uri>
        </author>
        <author>
            <name>Samer Adeeb</name>
            <uri>https://sameradeeb.srv.ualberta.ca/</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="Calculators" term="Calculators"/>
        <category label="Pharmacy" term="Pharmacy"/>
        <category label="Medicine" term="Medicine"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[CSA S16-19 CivE Calculators]]></title>
        <id>csa-calculators-2022</id>
        <link href="https://docs.mecsimcalc.com/blog/csa-calculators-2022"/>
        <updated>2022-06-10T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve spent the last month creating apps for the purpose of designing flexural members, compression members, tension members, and beam-columns in accordance with CSA S16-19.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve spent the last month creating apps for the purpose of designing flexural members, compression members, tension members, and beam-columns in accordance with CSA S16-19.</p><p>First, I had to learn Python. I took a 12-hour beginners course which was sufficient for learning the basics to Python, however not specific enough to be able to code the apps and get them to function as desired. Luckily, there are plenty of resources online and through watching YouTube tutorials, I was able to code the apps. Overall, learning python required lots of trial and error but was overall a smooth process due to the available resources.</p><p>I also had a very good experience using MecSimCalc as I found it incredibly easy to use and efficient, and it did not take long to adjust to.</p><p>Five applications have been created for design calculations in accordance with CSA S16-19. All applications require an input of the Cross Section, Yield Strength, and Unbraced Length of the member. The applications and their capabilities are presented below.</p><table><thead><tr><th>Calculator</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/4389397/design_of_flexural_members_with_w_section_csa_s_16_19" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Design of Flexural Members with W-Section</a></td><td>This application computes the Section Class, Plastic or Yield Flexural Moment, Factored Flexural Moment Resistance, and Factored Shear Resistance of W-Sections under uniformly distributed load. Along with the mentioned inputs, there is also a lateral support option. If the beam is laterally unsupported, the Equivalent Moment Factor and Critical Elastic Flexural Moment are also computed for the purpose of calculating the Factored Moment Resistance.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/7445336/design_of_compression_members_in_accordance_with_csa_s_16_19" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Design of Compression Members</a></td><td>This application checks the Width-to-Thickness Ratio, Slenderness, and computes the Factored Compression Resistance for W-Sections and HSS. Along with the general inputs for the CSA apps, there is also the option of support conditions, which is used to determine the Effective Length Factor in the Factored Compression Resistance calculations. If the compression member does not pass the Width-to-Thickness Ratio Check, the app stops there as the predicted resistance cannot actually be reached.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/0029258/design_of_tension_members_in_accordance_with_csa_s_16_19" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Design of Tension Members</a></td><td>This application calculates the Factored Tensile Resistance based on gross section yielding and performs a Serviceability Limit State (SLS) vibration check for W-Sections and HSS.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/3708352/w_shaped_beam_columns_under_major_axis_bending_csa_s_16_19" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">W-Section Beam-Columns under Major Axis Bending</a></td><td>This application performs the four limit state checks for Beam-Columns with W-Sections under major axis bending. Along with the general inputs, the app requires the user to input the Factored Compression Load, Smaller End Factored Moment, Larger End Factored Moment, Frame Type, and Moment Distribution. The four limit states that are checked are: Cross-Sectional Strength, Overall Member Strength, Lateral-Torsional Buckling Strength, and Moment Check.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/6568576/w_shaped_beam_columns_under_biaxial_bending_csa_s_16_19" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">W-Section Beam-Columns under Biaxial Bending</a></td><td>This application performs the four limit state checks for Beam-Columns with W-Sections under biaxial bending. The inputs and outputs are similar to the app for Beam-Columns under major axis bending.</td></tr></tbody></table>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Rana El Sadig</name>
        </author>
        <category label="Calculators" term="Calculators"/>
        <category label="Civil Engineering" term="Civil Engineering"/>
        <category label="Engineering" term="Engineering"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Starter Calculators]]></title>
        <id>starter-calculators-2021</id>
        <link href="https://docs.mecsimcalc.com/blog/starter-calculators-2021"/>
        <updated>2022-04-17T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[The following are free-to-use calculators developed by researchers at the University of Alberta for a variety of disciplines.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The following are free-to-use calculators developed by researchers at the University of Alberta for a variety of disciplines.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="civil-engineering">Civil Engineering<a class="hash-link" href="#civil-engineering" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><table><thead><tr><th>App</th><th>Category</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/8201998/csa_s_16_1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">CSA S16-1</a></td><td>Structural Engineering</td><td>An application to determine class, moments and maximum shear of W section Steel beams.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/0595262/csa_s_16_2" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">CSA S16-2</a></td><td>Structural Engineering</td><td>Gives all beams with specified input</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/0935172/csa_s_16_tension_member" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">CSA S16 Tension Member</a></td><td>Structural Engineering</td><td>CSA S16 Tension Member</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/0201297/csa_s_16_compression_member" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">CSA S16 Compression Member</a></td><td>Structural Engineering</td><td>CSA S16 Compression Member</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/9717102/csa_s_16_flexure" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">CSA S16 Flexure</a></td><td>Structural Engineering</td><td>CSA S16 Flexure</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/6888704/strain_demand_in_pipes_subjected_to_ground_movement" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Strain Demand in Pipes Subjected to Ground Movement</a></td><td>Pipeline Engineering</td><td>This page analyzes the response of the pipe to ground movements induced by geotechnical activities, e.g., ground heave and subsidence, slope instability, landslides, liquefaction-induced action, and tectonic faults.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/4446725/stress_design_of_straight_pipe_according_to_csa_z_662_19" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Stress Design of Straight Pipe According to CSA Z662.19</a></td><td>Pipeline Engineering</td><td>CSA Z662.19 provides equations limiting the circumferential and longitudinal stresses in steel pipelines. Given the pipe properties and field conditions, this page performs the required checks according to sections 4.3.5.1, 4.7, and 4.8.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/9389449/stress_strain_curve_of_steel_materials" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Stress Strain Curve of Steel Materials</a></td><td>Pipeline Engineering</td><td>This page calculates converts the Engineering stress-strain curve to true stress-strain curve using the well known conversion equations. The page outputs the stress-plastic strain data required by some finite element analysis software and provides the best-fit Ramberg-Osgood approximation to the given data.</td></tr></tbody></table><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="electrical-engineering">Electrical Engineering<a class="hash-link" href="#electrical-engineering" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><table><thead><tr><th>App</th><th>Category</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/5558606/processor_comparison" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Processor Comparison</a></td><td>Hardware Engineering</td><td>Compares two processors by utilizing benchmark times for different programs.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/8483456/discrete_signals_difference_equations" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Discrete Signals Difference Equations</a></td><td>Signal Processing</td><td>An application to determine values of a difference equation. Assumptions are sets the x(n)=δ(n) (the impulse function) and y(n)=0 for n&lt;0. Make sure n is greater than the size of Y coefficients.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/9697406/convolution" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Convolution</a></td><td>Signal Processing</td><td>An application to determine x<!-- -->[n]<!-- -->*<!-- -->h<!-- -->[n]<!-- --> = y<!-- -->[n]<!-- -->. The input contains the n index of each coefficient, such as the first element is n = 0 for the x function.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/1085971/circular_convolution" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Circular Convolution</a></td><td>Signal Processing</td><td>An application to determine the circular convolution of 2 functions.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/5513818/floating_point_binary_numbers" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Floating point binary numbers</a></td><td>Binary</td><td>Floating point numbers can be represented using IEEE 754 in binary. This system uses one sign bit, then a set number of exponent (k) bits and finally, fraction (n) bits. Depending on the number of these bits, the representations of numbers change as well. This calculator is made with the intention of getting the largest floating point number possible as well as the largest integer. There are restrictions on the number of bits that can be checked, due to an overflow possibility in python.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/0378917/hard_disk_drive_hdd_reading_a_file" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Hard Disk Drive (HDD) Reading a File</a></td><td>Hardware Engineering</td><td>Best and random cases of the time an HDD will take to read over a file. Assumes both block size and sector size are the same</td></tr></tbody></table><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="chemistry">Chemistry<a class="hash-link" href="#chemistry" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><table><thead><tr><th>App</th><th>Category</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/0663779/thermo_question_type_1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Thermo Question Type 1</a></td><td>Thermodynamics</td><td>An application to determine quality given certain knowns and unknowns. Known variable values must correspond to Thermo tables.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/1903331/thermo_question_type_2" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Thermo Question Type 2</a></td><td>Thermodynamics</td><td>An application to determine particular unknown given certain knowns. Known variable values must correspond to Thermo tables.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/2584336/thermo_question_type_1_b" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Thermo Question Type 1b</a></td><td>Thermodynamics</td><td>An application to determine a specific value given certain knowns and unknowns. Known variable values must correspond to Thermo tables.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/3069689/diagrams" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Diagrams</a></td><td>Thermodynamics</td><td>An application to graph Pv and Tv graphs.</td></tr></tbody></table><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="physics">Physics<a class="hash-link" href="#physics" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><table><thead><tr><th>App</th><th>Category</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/3152375/thin_lens_equation" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Thin Lens Equation</a></td><td>Optics</td><td>Knowing the distance an object is from a lens, we can determine the focal length and the magnification.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/9676607/thin_compound_lens_equation" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Thin Compound Lens Equation</a></td><td>Optics</td><td>We can find combined focal length of two lens. If d is input as being greater than f_1, then it will be assumed that d is 0.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/6017792/lensmaker_equation" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Lensmaker Equation</a></td><td>Optics</td><td>The lens maker equation can be used to find both the Power and focal length of a thick lens and a thin lens if the thickness tends to 0.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/1227912/snells_law" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Snell's Law</a></td><td>Optics</td><td>This application will derive the angle of refraction using Snell's Law.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/5545394/coulombs_law" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Coulomb's Law</a></td><td>Electrostatic</td><td>Coulomb's Law with three point charges</td></tr></tbody></table><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="business-and-finance">Business and Finance<a class="hash-link" href="#business-and-finance" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><table><thead><tr><th>App</th><th>Category</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/6285257/antique_lamps" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Antique Lamps</a></td><td>Max Profit Estimation</td><td>An application to maximize profits, with the given types of lamps, bass, and platinum. Maximize, has 2 inputs with their coefficients. Assembly has 3 inputs, each being its respective coefficients, and Max demand has 1 input. The coefficients are aB+ bP = cC where B is brass, P is platinum, and C is the constant, with the input <!-- -->[a,b,c]<!-- -->. The inputs are interpreted into functions where it is drawn on the graph. There will be a feasible region where all boundaries will be satisfied. The program then picks all the intersections within the feasible region(note that some points will not be accounted for). The output just gives the profits given at that point on the graph.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/4532115/cattle_profit" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Cattle Profit</a></td><td>Max Profit Estimation</td><td>An application to maximize profits (only gives boundaries), the first table consists of the first element being the regular, and the 2nd being the premium. The second table consists of the first element being alfalfa and the second being barley. This can also be translated such as the required material for a toy car to be inputted, but in this case it is just using cattle profit as the output. The program basically just gives the boundaries and conditions of what to expect before proceeding onto the next step.</td></tr></tbody></table>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Darius Fang</name>
        </author>
        <author>
            <name>Saif Husnain</name>
        </author>
        <author>
            <name>Qian Zheng</name>
        </author>
        <author>
            <name>Weichen Qiu</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/w3ichen</uri>
        </author>
        <author>
            <name>Samer Adeeb</name>
            <uri>https://sameradeeb.srv.ualberta.ca/</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="Calculators" term="Calculators"/>
        <category label="Engineering" term="Engineering"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to MecSimCalc]]></title>
        <id>welcome</id>
        <link href="https://docs.mecsimcalc.com/blog/welcome"/>
        <updated>2022-03-02T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to our newly released MecSimCalc platform for creating and sharing computational tools on the web. With a few very simple steps, educators and professionals can create interactive web applications for their students or clients.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to our newly released <strong>MecSimCalc</strong> platform for <strong>creating</strong> and <strong>sharing</strong> computational tools on the web. With a few very simple steps, educators and professionals can create interactive web applications for their students or clients.</p><p><strong>MecSimCalc</strong> has been a concept in my head since I joined the Engineering Faculty at the University of Alberta in 2007. At the time, I was looking for an easy way to create interactive web examples for my students to help them visualize different Mathematical and Engineering concepts. Throughout the years, I experimented with <a href="https://www.wolfram.com/products/webmathematica/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">webMathematica</a> and <a href="https://www.javascript.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">javascripts</a>. However, dealing with web infrastructure has always been a struggle. I still remember the agony of trying to switch my whole website from traditional HTTP to HTTPS or the yearly agony of renewing the licenses of the different components that I was using. Throughout the years, my experience has shaped my vision for creating <strong>MecSimCalc</strong> as a platform that frees the developer from all the ever changing web architecture to allow them to focus on their application.</p><p><strong>MecSimCalc</strong> is a simple, yet extremely powerful platform that has applications in a large array of fields. Here is an example in <a href="https://www.mecsimcalc.com/app/7188609/diabetes_risk" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Medicine</a>, by answering a simple questionnaire, a visitor to the app can identify their diabetes risk. The app was created based on an algorithm published on a <a href="https://www.healthycanadians.gc.ca/en/canrisk" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Canadian government website</a>. For University Mathematics <a href="https://www.mecsimcalc.com/app/4730621/numerical_integration" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Education</a>, a student can enter any functional expression and the limits of an integral while the interactive app would calculate the numerical integral and would provide a plot, powered by <code>matplotlib</code> for visual illustration of the example.</p><p>We created <strong>MecSimCalc</strong> for professionals in engineering and finance. Consider the <a href="https://www.mecsimcalc.com/app/3333910/mortgage_calculator" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">app</a> that can be distributed by a mortgage specialist to his or her clients to help them identify the price of the house that matches their finances. Or consider the <a href="https://www.mecsimcalc.com/app/8106967/cor_las_model" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Engineering app</a> that uses the <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/309917227_Review_of_Engineering_Fracture_Mechanics_Model_for_Pipeline_Applications" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">CorLAS</a> algorithm to calculate the failure pressure of pipelines with longitudinal crack like features. While these apps are currently publicly available, we can work with any professionals to help them build and share their specific applications only with their clients.</p><p>I welcome all our visitors to <a href="https://www.mecsimcalc.com/explore" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">explore</a> the different applications that have been created using <strong>MecSimCalc</strong>.</p><p>We also invite all professionals, scientists, and educators who would like to publicly or privately publish their lively algorithms to try out our <strong>free</strong> platform. We promise to keep it free for any publicly available applications. We are also happy to work with any professionals wishing to use <strong>MecSimCalc</strong> for their enterprise applications.</p><p>Please send us any suggestions, questions, or inquiries to <a href="mailto:info@mecsimcalc.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">info@mecsimcalc.com</a></p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Samer Adeeb</name>
            <uri>https://sameradeeb.srv.ualberta.ca/</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="MecSimCalc" term="MecSimCalc"/>
    </entry>
</feed>