<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>MecSimCalc Docs Blog</title>
        <link>https://docs.mecsimcalc.com/blog</link>
        <description>MecSimCalc Docs Blog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 22 Oct 2022 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[MecSimCalc Build-A-Thon (October 8th - October 15th, 2022) Winners]]></title>
            <link>https://docs.mecsimcalc.com/blog/Comp07092022-Winners</link>
            <guid>Comp07092022-Winners</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 22 Oct 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[After the success of MecSimCalc's first hackathon in July, we had decided to run a Hackathon each month starting in October. This competition sponsored by 1984 Ventures, was aimed to increase the number of users and showcase the versatility of the platform. Users would create an app on the MecSimCalc website, tag it as "Comp10082022" and publish it for a chance to win $100.  Throughout the competition there were 56 sign-ups and 16 submissions. This blog post is dedicated to the top 5 scoring apps from MecSimCalc's October 8th - October 15th, 2022 Build-A-Thon 2.0. To view all apps submitted during the competition on MecSimCalc, look for the tag "Comp10082022" on the MecSimCalc Search page.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>After the success of MecSimCalc's first hackathon in July, we had decided to run a Hackathon each month starting in October. This competition sponsored by 1984 Ventures, was aimed to increase the number of users and showcase the versatility of the platform. Users would create an app on the MecSimCalc website, tag it as "Comp10082022" and publish it for a chance to win $100.  Throughout the competition there were 56 sign-ups and 16 submissions. This blog post is dedicated to the top 5 scoring apps from MecSimCalc's October 8th - October 15th, 2022 Build-A-Thon 2.0. To view all apps submitted during the competition on MecSimCalc, look for the tag "Comp10082022" on the MecSimCalc Search page.</p><p><img loading="lazy" alt="Hackathon 2.0 Poster" src="/assets/images/MecSimCalc_Hackathon_2-de1cc00cdd39205ded732eb25f4a2065.png" width="1080" height="1080" class="img_ev3q"></p><table><thead><tr><th>App</th><th>Author(s)</th><th>Win</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/3128476/quadratic_equations_solver" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Quadratic Equations Solver</a></td><td>Zouhair Fakhoury</td><td>Grand Prize Winner ($100)</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/6185690/quality_of_life_app" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Quality of Life App</a></td><td>Anika Krishnan</td><td>Top 5 App</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/0866015/your_trip_buddy" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Your Trip Buddy</a></td><td>Vaibhav Thalanki</td><td>Top 5 App</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/3166730/sudoku_solver" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Sudoku Solver</a></td><td>Michael Jean</td><td>Top 5 App</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/7698150/auto_base_64_decode" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Auto Base64 Decode</a></td><td>Noah Ergezinger</td><td>Top 5 App</td></tr></tbody></table><hr><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="quadratic-equations-solver-winner"><strong><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/3128476/quadratic_equations_solver" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Quadratic Equations Solver (WINNER)</a></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#quadratic-equations-solver-winner" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><hr><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="about-zouhair-fakhoury"><strong><em>About Zouhair Fakhoury</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#about-zouhair-fakhoury" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Hi, this is Zouhair! I'm a Lebanese senior high school student passionate about coding and motorsports. I started programming at 14 years old with Python. I like other tech disciplines such as Cybersecurity, Arduino, and multi-platform app development. I'm planning on following a major in Computer Science to specialize in Software Engineering. </p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="about-my-app"><strong><em>About My App</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#about-my-app" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Being a math passionate, I've always wondered if I could automate some mathematical processes of solving problems. I knew there was something that we use more often than we realize: the quadratic functions.
Hence, on the occasion of MecSimCalc's Hackathon 2.0, I made a Quadratic Equations Solver. As its name suggests, it solves quadratic equations in their standard form: ax² + bx + c = 0, providing you with analytical and descriptive results to help you find solutions easily.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="my-experience-with-mecsimcalc"><strong><em>My experience with MecSimCalc</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#my-experience-with-mecsimcalc" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>I'm so grateful for joining MecSimCalc. I've had a wonderful experience working in its coding environment. MecSimCalc solves the hard side of creating GUIs with a drag-and-drop solution. The interface is very intuitive and easy to understand. It has more features than I expected like the integration of LaTeX, geospatial utilities, handling files and processing images, etc... The best part is that you don't need prior experience in web development. You can simply create a Python web app and deploy it instantly within minutes!</p><hr><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="quality-of-life-app"><strong><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/6185690/quality_of_life_app" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Quality of Life App</a></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#quality-of-life-app" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><hr><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="about-anika-krishnan"><strong><em>About Anika Krishnan</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#about-anika-krishnan" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>I am a high schooler in Redmond, WA, USA. I love to build social and community apps, especially apps that use data science/analytics.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="about-my-app-1"><strong><em>About My App</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#about-my-app-1" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>At this time, Air quality in my area is poor and some of my friends that have asthma/allergies are having to temporarily move to other locations. This was the inspiration for the idea. When one moves to a city, many things are important for your quality of your life, eg.: Air Quality, Safety, Traffic, Covid Risk, Cost of Milk and Eggs, Housing costs and more.. Wouldn't it be nice to know how the city measures on all the things that are important to you? The Quality of Life app uses many sources to gather data and calculate scores in different areas like air quality, pollen, job climate so you can visualize all the data and make informed decisions.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="my-experience-with-mecsimcalc-1"><strong><em>My experience with MecSimCalc</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#my-experience-with-mecsimcalc-1" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>It was very easy to get started. The examples and tutorials were very helpful. It took very little time to have the triangle example working. While building the application, I really appreciated being able to write the code and test it directly in the browser and was able to build a good app with some UI during the hackathon. Things that would make this platform more powerful include being able to more during inputs ( html/js), more support for additional libraries ( maybe allow users to add). It was a bit hard to debug ( being able to step through Jupyter notebooks may be useful). Overall I really enjoyed this experience and being able to build an app with UI and inputs/outputs without having to learn about all the other systems.</p><hr><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="your-trip-buddy"><strong><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/0866015/your_trip_buddy" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Your Trip Buddy</a></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#your-trip-buddy" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><hr><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="about-vaibhav-thalanki"><strong><em>About Vaibhav Thalanki</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#about-vaibhav-thalanki" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>I am Vaibhav Thalanki from Chennai, India. I am currently pursuing my undergraduate in computer science at VIT University. Some things I am very much interested in are deep learning and product development. I have participated in quite a few hackathons before this one. I also attended the previous MecSlimCalc buildathon.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="about-my-app-2"><strong><em>About My App</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#about-my-app-2" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>The app that I created for this hackathon is called 'Your Trip Buddy', it gives you information about the weather, airports, and time zones for your trip's destination. I used a few APIs for building the app. It eases the process by collecting information from different sources and putting it in a friendly format for the user to read. </p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="my-experience-with-mecsimcalc-2"><strong><em>My experience with MecSimCalc</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#my-experience-with-mecsimcalc-2" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>MecSimCalc is an amazing platform to work on and explore. The professor and the students behind the MecSlimCalc project have succeeded in their goals. The website is simply brilliant and I would be using it for a lot more stuff. Ciao!</p><hr><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="auto-base64-decode"><strong><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/7698150/auto_base_64_decode" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Auto Base64 Decode</a></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#auto-base64-decode" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><hr><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="about-noah-ergezinger"><strong><em>About Noah Ergezinger</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#about-noah-ergezinger" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>I graduated in December 2021 and started working full-time at Ezoic this past February. I actually worked on this website during one of the summer breaks while in university, so I was very excited when they announced the Buildathon. It was great to see the progress made since I had last worked on it and that it was seeing lots of use.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="about-my-app-3"><strong><em>About My App</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#about-my-app-3" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>In a nutshell, Auto Base64 Decode takes a string, finds any base64-encoded portions, decodes them, and inserts them back into the original string. I made my app because it was actually something I needed at work. Many of our web requests contain encoded data, and when debugging, we constantly need to copy the data into a decoder, which gets tedious. I thought it would be great to be able to automatically decode the relevant portions without needing to copy each one by hand. I've shared it with my team, and we've already been using it a ton.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="my-experience-with-mecsimcalc-3"><strong><em>My experience with MecSimCalc</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#my-experience-with-mecsimcalc-3" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Building a script or tool and easily sharing it was precisely the original use case for MecSimCalc, and I'm happy to see that come to fruition. I look forward to what comes next, and I hope the MecSimCalc team sees nothing but success!</p><hr><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="we-are-hosting-another-hackathon-in-from-november-5th---november-12th-2022-please-check-out-the-devpost-to-find-out-more"><strong>We are hosting another hackathon in from November 5th - November 12th 2022, please check out the <a href="https://mecsimcalc-hackathon-3.devpost.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">DevPost</a> to find out more!</strong><a class="hash-link" href="#we-are-hosting-another-hackathon-in-from-november-5th---november-12th-2022-please-check-out-the-devpost-to-find-out-more" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p><img loading="lazy" alt="Hackathon 3.0 Poster" src="/assets/images/MecSimCalc_Presents_3-06ff5b1864d230cb84b0f2afd60f7be9.png" width="1728" height="2304" class="img_ev3q"></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>MecSimCalc</category>
            <category>Comp10082022</category>
            <category>hackathon</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Johns Yu's Apps 2]]></title>
            <link>https://docs.mecsimcalc.com/blog/JohnYu-apps2</link>
            <guid>JohnYu-apps2</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[The following blogposts were written by John Yu for apps he had created on MecSimCalc. John Yu was a student researcher working with MecSimCalc for 8 months. We will miss you John!]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The following blogposts were written by John Yu for apps he had created on MecSimCalc. John Yu was a student researcher working with MecSimCalc for 8 months. We will miss you John!</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="algebraic-operation-on-complex-numbers"><strong>Algebraic Operation on Complex Numbers</strong><a class="hash-link" href="#algebraic-operation-on-complex-numbers" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>This blog post is dedicated to the <a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/3941579/algebraic_operations_on_complex_numbers" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Algebraic Operation on Complex Numbers</a> app created by John Yu.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="about-the-app"><strong><em>About the app</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#about-the-app" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>The Algebraic Operation on Complex Numbers app is intended for students taking a linear
algebra course. This app helps students better grasp how operations are performed with
complex numbers. The app lets you perform 4 types of operations: addition, subtraction,
multiplication, and division. Addition and subtraction using complex numbers is best performed
using vectors and the app walks users through the steps using visual aids. Multiplication and
division using complex numbers is best performed using euler form and the app provides
excellent visual aids to assist students in learning the step-by-step process. Learning how to
perform operations on complex numbers is very important for any engineering student.
Complex numbers have many practical applications particularly in electrical and computer
engineering where these skills will be invaluable. Students who use this app will find themselves
better prepared for their future engineering courses.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="understanding-vector-fields"><strong>Understanding Vector Fields</strong><a class="hash-link" href="#understanding-vector-fields" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>This blog post is dedicated to the <a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/9890961/understanding_vector_fields" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Understanding Vector Fields</a> app created by John Yu.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="about-the-app-1"><strong><em>About the app</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#about-the-app-1" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>The Understanding Vector Fields app lets you visually generate a vector field. The app takes in
an equation representing your vector field and plots each vector on a graph. It is useful in a
variety of applications. Vector calculus is a very important skill and many engineering students
take a calculus class dedicated to this subject. You can plot simple equations like the flow of a
river with the equation . You can plot more complicated vector fields like a magnetic field using
the equation .</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>MecSimCalc</category>
            <category>Engineering</category>
            <category>Math</category>
            <category>Linear Algebra</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Vivid Hacks v1.5 MecSimCalc Workshop]]></title>
            <link>https://docs.mecsimcalc.com/blog/Vivid-Hacks-1.5-MecSimCalc-Workshop</link>
            <guid>Vivid-Hacks-1.5-MecSimCalc-Workshop</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[This blog post is dedicated to the MecSimCalc Workshop for the Vivid Hacks v1.5 Hackathon on August 6th, 2022. For more info on Vivid Hacks visit Vivid Hacks and to see the project gallery for the hackathon visit their DevPost.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This blog post is dedicated to the MecSimCalc Workshop for the Vivid Hacks v1.5 Hackathon on August 6th, 2022. For more info on Vivid Hacks visit <a href="https://www.vividhacks.tech/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Vivid Hacks</a> and to see the project gallery for the hackathon visit their <a href="https://vividhacks-1-5.devpost.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">DevPost</a>.</p><p>This is a recording of the workshop detailing how to use MecSimCalc. In this workshop, I create a simple app that returns the product of two variables and prints a message in the output specified by the user. The entire process for making an app on MecSimCalc from start to publishing is shown and takes around 10 mintues. Make sure to visit the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCh9c4pzjNCNsHMJyv8uYczw/featured" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MecSimCalc YouTube Channel</a> and subscribe.</p><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/EvyC54PfJO4" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture"></iframe>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>MecSimCalc</category>
            <category>hackathon</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[John Yu's Apps]]></title>
            <link>https://docs.mecsimcalc.com/blog/JohnYu-apps</link>
            <guid>JohnYu-apps</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[The following blogposts were written by John Yu for various apps he had created on MecSimCalc.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The following blogposts were written by John Yu for various apps he had created on MecSimCalc. </p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="pairwise-testing-generator"><strong>Pairwise Testing Generator</strong><a class="hash-link" href="#pairwise-testing-generator" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>This blog post is dedicated to the <a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/8809236/pairwise_testing_generator" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pairwise Testing Generator</a> app created by John Yu.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="about-the-pairwise-testing-generator"><strong><em>About the Pairwise Testing Generator</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#about-the-pairwise-testing-generator" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>The pairwise testing generator is an app that can generate a set of test cases with up to 5
independent variables. The app uses a technique called Taguchi Orthogonal Arrays such that
every pairing of variables appears in at least one test case. This method is significantly more
powerful and more efficient compared to brute-force testing. You can get full testing coverage
of your program using significantly less test cases. This can save you a lot of time and a lot of
money depending on the size of your program.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="why-i-made-this-app"><strong><em>Why I made this app</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#why-i-made-this-app" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Software testing is a critical step in the software development lifecycle. There are countless
opportunities for mistakes and defects to come up at any point in the development of software.
Fixing code is equally as important as creating code. Finding these bugs early in the
development lifecycle will help to mitigate issues that come up later. The hard part of testing
code is generating test cases. Full code coverage often comes with a huge set of test cases
which is expensive and time consuming. A small set of test cases is cost effective but lacks code
coverage. I made this app to help software engineers generate test cases that can provide
adequate code coverage in a reasonable amount of test cases. This saves you a lot of time and
money and improves the quality of your code.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="simple-linear-regression-and-discrete-probability-distribution"><strong>Simple Linear Regression and Discrete Probability Distribution</strong><a class="hash-link" href="#simple-linear-regression-and-discrete-probability-distribution" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>This blog post is dedicated to the <a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/3625435/simple_linear_regression" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Simple Linear Regression</a> and <a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/8359657/visualizing_discrete_probability_distributions" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Visualizing Discrete Probability Distributions</a> apps created by John Yu.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="about-the-simple-linear-regression-and-the-discrete-probability-distribution-app"><strong><em>About the Simple Linear Regression and the Discrete Probability Distribution App</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#about-the-simple-linear-regression-and-the-discrete-probability-distribution-app" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>The simple linear regression app can generate a regression line from your set of data points.
The app is intended to be a helpful tool for Statistics students to understand how the linear
regression line is calculated. There are no statistical libraries used in the calculation of the
regression line. All calculations are done using equations from my statistics textbook. The app
will calculate the regression line as well as show you how the calculation is performed. In
statistics, there are many formulas that can calculate a regression line. This app uses the
simplest equation to help students gain a better understanding of how the regression line is
calculated.</p><p>The Discrete Probability Distribution app can visualize common probability distributions in
Statistics. This app is intended to be a helpful tool for students taking Statistics to understand
how these probability distributions work. The user can play around with the parameters of the
distributions defined in the app inputs to understand how these parameters impact the graph.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="truth-table-generator"><strong>Truth Table Generator</strong><a class="hash-link" href="#truth-table-generator" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>This blog post is dedicated to the <a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/4669459/truth_table_generator" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Truth Table Generator</a> app created by John Yu.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="about-the-truth-table-generator-app"><strong><em>About the Truth Table Generator App</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#about-the-truth-table-generator-app" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>The truth table generator is an app that can generate a truth table by defining a logical
expression. You can define a logic expression simply by typing it into the app inputs. The app
will evaluate your expression with each possible combination of inputs and return the expected
output. This app is intended to be used by students taking a digital logic class who need to
quickly generate a truth table. Sometimes a logic expression may be very complicated to
evaluate by hand. This app can generate a truth table with any expression no matter how
complicated it is. Students will find this app by helpful for verifying your truth table. The app
has been tested multiple times to ensure that the expected outputs are correct.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>MecSimCalc</category>
            <category>Computer Science</category>
            <category>Engineering</category>
            <category>Math</category>
            <category>Statistics</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Useful Webtools]]></title>
            <link>https://docs.mecsimcalc.com/blog/websiteplanet-2022</link>
            <guid>websiteplanet-2022</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[This blogpost is dedicated to webtools developed by WebsitePlanet. You can visit all of their webtools at WebsitePlanet.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This blogpost is dedicated to webtools developed by WebsitePlanet. You can visit all of their webtools at <a href="https://www.websiteplanet.com/webtools/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">WebsitePlanet</a>.</p><table><thead><tr><th>App</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><a href="https://www.websiteplanet.com/webtools/jscssminifier/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">JS and CSS Minifier</a></td><td>This tool makes your website run faster and take up less data by "minifying" the JavaScript and CSS code.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://www.websiteplanet.com/webtools/unminify-js/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">JS and CSS Unminifier</a></td><td>This tool unminifies JavaScript and CSS code to be more readable for users.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://www.websiteplanet.com/webtools/imagecompressor/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Image Compressor</a></td><td>This tool compresses PNG/JPG images to up to 80% of it's original size, lowering it's data size.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://www.websiteplanet.com/webtools/free-qr-code-generator/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">QR Code Generator</a></td><td>This tool creates a custom, high-resolution QR code that directs users to websites, emails, social media sites and more.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://www.websiteplanet.com/webtools/favicon-generator/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Favicon Generator</a></td><td>This tool automatically resizes an image to a favicon in PNG format.</td></tr></tbody></table>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[MecSimCalc Build-A-Thon (July 9th - July 16th, 2022) Winners]]></title>
            <link>https://docs.mecsimcalc.com/blog/Comp07092022-Winners</link>
            <guid>Comp07092022-Winners</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[MecSimCalc had it's first ever hackathon in July 2022. This competition sponsored by 1984 Ventures, was aimed to increase the number of users and showcase the versatility of the platform. Users would create an app on the MecSimCalc website, tag it as "Comp07092022" and publish it for a chance to win up to $500. $400 would be given to the app with the highest score and $100 would be given to the most viewed app. However, since we had received so many high quality submissions, three additional bonus prizes were given out to apps that had not won but were innovative uses of the platform. Throughout the competition there were 77 sign-ups and 13 submissions. This blog post is dedicated to the top 5 scoring apps from MecSimCalc's July 9th - July 16th, 2022 Build-A-Thon. To view all apps submitted during the competition, look for the tag "Comp07092022" on the MecSimCalc Explore page.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>After the success of MecSimCalc's first hackathon in July, we had decided to run a Hackathon each month starting in October. This competition sponsored by 1984 Ventures, was aimed to increase the number of users and showcase the versatility of the platform. Users would create an app on the MecSimCalc website, tag it as "Comp10082022" and publish it for a chance to win $100.  Throughout the competition there were 56 sign-ups and 16 submissions. This blog post is dedicated to the top 5 scoring apps from MecSimCalc's October 8th - October 15th, 2022 Build-A-Thon 2.0. To view all apps submitted during the competition on MecSimCalc, look for the tag "Comp10082022" on the MecSimCalc Search page.</p><p><img loading="lazy" alt="Hackathon 2.0 Poster" src="/assets/images/MecSimCalc_Hackathon_2-de1cc00cdd39205ded732eb25f4a2065.png" width="1080" height="1080" class="img_ev3q"></p><table><thead><tr><th>App</th><th>Author(s)</th><th>Win</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/3128476/quadratic_equations_solver" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Quadratic Equations Solver</a></td><td>Zouhair Fakhoury</td><td>Grand Prize Winner ($100)</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/6185690/quality_of_life_app" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Quality of Life App</a></td><td>Anika Krishnan</td><td>Top 5 App</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/0866015/your_trip_buddy" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Your Trip Buddy</a></td><td>Vaibhav Thalanki</td><td>Top 5 App</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/3166730/sudoku_solver" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Sudoku Solver</a></td><td>Michael Jean</td><td>Top 5 App</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/7698150/auto_base_64_decode" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Auto Base64 Decode</a></td><td>Noah Ergezinger</td><td>Top 5 App</td></tr></tbody></table><hr><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="quadratic-equations-solver-winner"><strong><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/3128476/quadratic_equations_solver" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Quadratic Equations Solver (WINNER)</a></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#quadratic-equations-solver-winner" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><hr><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="about-zouhair-fakhoury"><strong><em>About Zouhair Fakhoury</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#about-zouhair-fakhoury" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Hi, this is Zouhair! I'm a Lebanese senior high school student passionate about coding and motorsports. I started programming at 14 years old with Python. I like other tech disciplines such as Cybersecurity, Arduino, and multi-platform app development. I'm planning on following a major in Computer Science to specialize in Software Engineering. </p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="about-my-app"><strong><em>About My App</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#about-my-app" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Being a math passionate, I've always wondered if I could automate some mathematical processes of solving problems. I knew there was something that we use more often than we realize: the quadratic functions.
Hence, on the occasion of MecSimCalc's Hackathon 2.0, I made a Quadratic Equations Solver. As its name suggests, it solves quadratic equations in their standard form: ax² + bx + c = 0, providing you with analytical and descriptive results to help you find solutions easily.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="my-experience-with-mecsimcalc"><strong><em>My experience with MecSimCalc</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#my-experience-with-mecsimcalc" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>I'm so grateful for joining MecSimCalc. I've had a wonderful experience working in its coding environment. MecSimCalc solves the hard side of creating GUIs with a drag-and-drop solution. The interface is very intuitive and easy to understand. It has more features than I expected like the integration of LaTeX, geospatial utilities, handling files and processing images, etc... The best part is that you don't need prior experience in web development. You can simply create a Python web app and deploy it instantly within minutes!</p><hr><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="quality-of-life-app"><strong><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/6185690/quality_of_life_app" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Quality of Life App</a></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#quality-of-life-app" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><hr><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="about-anika-krishnan"><strong><em>About Anika Krishnan</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#about-anika-krishnan" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>I am a high schooler in Redmond, WA, USA. I love to build social and community apps, especially apps that use data science/analytics.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="about-my-app-1"><strong><em>About My App</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#about-my-app-1" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>At this time, Air quality in my area is poor and some of my friends that have asthma/allergies are having to temporarily move to other locations. This was the inspiration for the idea. When one moves to a city, many things are important for your quality of your life, eg.: Air Quality, Safety, Traffic, Covid Risk, Cost of Milk and Eggs, Housing costs and more.. Wouldn't it be nice to know how the city measures on all the things that are important to you? The Quality of Life app uses many sources to gather data and calculate scores in different areas like air quality, pollen, job climate so you can visualize all the data and make informed decisions.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="my-experience-with-mecsimcalc-1"><strong><em>My experience with MecSimCalc</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#my-experience-with-mecsimcalc-1" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>It was very easy to get started. The examples and tutorials were very helpful. It took very little time to have the triangle example working. While building the application, I really appreciated being able to write the code and test it directly in the browser and was able to build a good app with some UI during the hackathon. Things that would make this platform more powerful include being able to more during inputs ( html/js), more support for additional libraries ( maybe allow users to add). It was a bit hard to debug ( being able to step through Jupyter notebooks may be useful). Overall I really enjoyed this experience and being able to build an app with UI and inputs/outputs without having to learn about all the other systems.</p><hr><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="your-trip-buddy"><strong><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/0866015/your_trip_buddy" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Your Trip Buddy</a></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#your-trip-buddy" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><hr><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="about-vaibhav-thalanki"><strong><em>About Vaibhav Thalanki</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#about-vaibhav-thalanki" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>I am Vaibhav Thalanki from Chennai, India. I am currently pursuing my undergraduate in computer science at VIT University. Some things I am very much interested in are deep learning and product development. I have participated in quite a few hackathons before this one. I also attended the previous MecSlimCalc buildathon.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="about-my-app-2"><strong><em>About My App</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#about-my-app-2" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>The app that I created for this hackathon is called 'Your Trip Buddy', it gives you information about the weather, airports, and time zones for your trip's destination. I used a few APIs for building the app. It eases the process by collecting information from different sources and putting it in a friendly format for the user to read. </p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="my-experience-with-mecsimcalc-2"><strong><em>My experience with MecSimCalc</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#my-experience-with-mecsimcalc-2" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>MecSimCalc is an amazing platform to work on and explore. The professor and the students behind the MecSlimCalc project have succeeded in their goals. The website is simply brilliant and I would be using it for a lot more stuff. Ciao!</p><hr><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="auto-base64-decode"><strong><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/7698150/auto_base_64_decode" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Auto Base64 Decode</a></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#auto-base64-decode" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><hr><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="about-noah-ergezinger"><strong><em>About Noah Ergezinger</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#about-noah-ergezinger" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>I graduated in December 2021 and started working full-time at Ezoic this past February. I actually worked on this website during one of the summer breaks while in university, so I was very excited when they announced the Buildathon. It was great to see the progress made since I had last worked on it and that it was seeing lots of use.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="about-my-app-3"><strong><em>About My App</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#about-my-app-3" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>In a nutshell, Auto Base64 Decode takes a string, finds any base64-encoded portions, decodes them, and inserts them back into the original string. I made my app because it was actually something I needed at work. Many of our web requests contain encoded data, and when debugging, we constantly need to copy the data into a decoder, which gets tedious. I thought it would be great to be able to automatically decode the relevant portions without needing to copy each one by hand. I've shared it with my team, and we've already been using it a ton.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="my-experience-with-mecsimcalc-3"><strong><em>My experience with MecSimCalc</em></strong><a class="hash-link" href="#my-experience-with-mecsimcalc-3" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Building a script or tool and easily sharing it was precisely the original use case for MecSimCalc, and I'm happy to see that come to fruition. I look forward to what comes next, and I hope the MecSimCalc team sees nothing but success!</p><hr><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="we-are-hosting-another-hackathon-in-from-november-5th---november-12th-2022-please-check-out-the-devpost-to-find-out-more"><strong>We are hosting another hackathon in from November 5th - November 12th 2022, please check out the <a href="https://mecsimcalc-hackathon-3.devpost.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">DevPost</a> to find out more!</strong><a class="hash-link" href="#we-are-hosting-another-hackathon-in-from-november-5th---november-12th-2022-please-check-out-the-devpost-to-find-out-more" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p><img loading="lazy" alt="Hackathon 3.0 Poster" src="/assets/images/MecSimCalc_Presents_3-06ff5b1864d230cb84b0f2afd60f7be9.png" width="1728" height="2304" class="img_ev3q"></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>MecSimCalc</category>
            <category>Comp07092022</category>
            <category>hackathon</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Masonry Calculators]]></title>
            <link>https://docs.mecsimcalc.com/blog/masonry-calculators-2022</link>
            <guid>masonry-calculators-2022</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Masonry is the building of structures from individual units, which are often laid in and bound together by mortar.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p><strong>Masonry</strong> is the building of structures from individual units, which are often laid in and bound together by mortar.</p></blockquote><p><img loading="lazy" alt="masonry" src="/assets/images/masonry-134ec92294f58c2911b22e497dd3a744.jpeg" width="1000" height="449" class="img_ev3q"></p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="authors">Authors<a class="hash-link" href="#authors" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p><strong>Dr. Mark D. Hagel</strong> is the Executive Director of Alberta Masonry Council and has kindly made his masonry calculators available on MecSimCalc.
Mark holds a Bachelor of Science in Actuarial Science and Applied Mathematics, a Bachelor of Science in Civil Engineering, and a Doctor of Philosophy in Civil Engineering all from the University of Calgary. Mark’s fields of expertise include thermal and hygrothermal modeling of building systems, corrosion modeling, Life Cycle Cost Analysis, structural analysis and design, and the durability of building components. In 2018 Mark served on the National Research Council of Canada’s (NRC) working group that developed the Guideline on Design for Durability of the Building Envelope.</p><p><strong>John Yu</strong> is a university researcher who converted Dr. Hagel's excel files into MecSimCalc apps.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="thermal-calculation-apps">Thermal calculation apps<a class="hash-link" href="#thermal-calculation-apps" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><table><thead><tr><th>Thermal calculation app</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/6855626/bvcu_thermal_catalog_app" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">BVCU Thermal Catalog App</a></td><td>An App that calculates the clear field (Uo) and linear transmittance (psi) values for foundation, floor, parapet corner and window/doors for Brick Veneer Concrete Block Unit (BVCU) wall systems for any value of exterior insulation. These values are needed to thermal bridging calculations to comply with the National Energy Code for Buildings (NECB).</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/1652032/bvws_thermal_catalog_app" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">BVWS Thermal Catalog App</a></td><td>An App that calculates the clear field Uo and linear transmittance values for foundation, floor, parapet corner and window/doors for Brick Veneer Concrete Block Unit (BVCU) wall systems for any value of exterior insulation. These values are needed to thermal bridging calculations to comply with the National Energy Code for Buildings (NECB).</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/6727343/bvss_thermal_catalog_app" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">BVSS Thermal Catalog App</a></td><td>An App that calculates the clear field Uo and linear transmittance values for foundation, floor, parapet corner and window/doors for Brick Veneer Steel Stud (BVSS) wall systems for any value of exterior insulation. These values are needed to thermal bridging calculations to comply with the National Energy Code for Buildings (NECB).</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/7431858/thermal_bridging_assembly_calculation" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Thermal Bridging Assembly Calculation</a></td><td>An App based on the BC hydro/Fortis/Powersmart “Enhanced Thermal Performance Spreadsheet”. The app calculates the impact on the clear field of a wall elevation from the thermal bridging effects of linear transmittances (foundation, floor, roof, corner, window/doors) and point transmittances (signage, etc.)</td></tr></tbody></table><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="life-cycle-cost-analysis-apps">Life cycle cost analysis apps<a class="hash-link" href="#life-cycle-cost-analysis-apps" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><table><thead><tr><th>Life cycle cost analysis app</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/3605070/cladding_life_cost_comparison" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Cladding Life Cost Comparison</a></td><td>An App that calculates the cost of up to three different cladding systems for a given building service life, inflation rate and discount rate using Life Cycle Cost Analysis (LCCA).</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/8921970/building_envelope_life_cost_comparison_calculator" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Building Envelope Life Cost Comparison Calculator</a></td><td>An App that calculates the cost of up to three different cladding AND roofing systems for a given building service life, inflation rate and discount rate using Life Cycle Cost Analysis (LCCA).</td></tr></tbody></table><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="carbon-sequestration-apps">Carbon sequestration apps<a class="hash-link" href="#carbon-sequestration-apps" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><table><thead><tr><th>Carbon sequestration app</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/9771381/cmu_block_wall_carbon_calculator" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">CMU Block Wall Carbon Calculator</a></td><td>An App to calculate the amount of carbon sequestered when constructing with concrete block masonry.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/2907334/brick_veneer_carbon_calculator" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Brick Veneer Carbon Calculator</a></td><td>An App to calculate the amount of carbon sequestered when constructing with clay brick veneer.</td></tr></tbody></table>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Calculators</category>
            <category>Civil Engineering</category>
            <category>Engineering</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Circuit Analysis Calculators]]></title>
            <link>https://docs.mecsimcalc.com/blog/electrical-calculators-2022</link>
            <guid>electrical-calculators-2022</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[This blog post is dedicated to circuit analysis calculators created for MecSimCalc.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This blog post is dedicated to circuit analysis calculators created for MecSimCalc.</p><table><thead><tr><th>App</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/2144200/voltage_divider_calculator" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Voltage Divider Calculator</a></td><td>This is an app for a voltage divider circuit. The user first inputs the input voltage (V), and the values of two resistors (Ω, kΩ, MΩ). Using the inputs and the voltage divider equation, the output voltage (V) measured across resistor 2 is returned.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/9979869/current_divider_calculator" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Current Divider Calculator</a></td><td>This is an app for a current divider circuit. The user inputs an input voltage (V) and the values of up to 5 resistors (Ω) in parallel. After finding the total current, the calculator uses the current divider equation to generate a table showing the various current (A) flowing through each resistor.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/8349728/op_amp_gain_and_output_voltage_calculator" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Op-Amp Gain and Output Voltage Calculator</a></td><td>Operational amplifiers are an active circuit component commonly used in various circuits. This app uses an op-amp in two common configurations, an inverting and non-inverting amplifier. The user selects which configuration they are using, the value of the input resistor (Ω, kΩ, MΩ), the feedback resistor (Ω, kΩ, MΩ) and the input voltage (V). Depending on the circuit chosen, a gain and the corresponding output voltage is calculated and displayed as well as an image of the circuit schematic.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/8934998/parallel_resistance_calculator" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Parallel Resistance Calculator</a></td><td>This app calculates the equivalent resistance of a circuit containing resistors in parallel. The user inputs up to 8 resistors (Ω) and using the parallel resistance equation, an equivalent resistance for the circuit is returned.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/7370385/resistor_color_code_calculator" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Resistor Color Code Calculator (4 Band)</a></td><td>This app decodes the value of a 4 band axial lead resistor. The user selects 4 colors (left to right), and the corresponding resistance value and tolerance is given.</td></tr></tbody></table>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Calculators</category>
            <category>Electrical Engineering</category>
            <category>Engineering</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Pharmacy Tools]]></title>
            <link>https://docs.mecsimcalc.com/blog/pharmacy-tools-2022</link>
            <guid>pharmacy-tools-2022</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 19 Jun 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[At MecSimCalc, our hope is to bring industries still using spreadsheets and PDFs online. With MecSimCalc, it is now possible to share tools easier and run calculations faster than ever before.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>At MecSimCalc, our hope is to bring industries still using spreadsheets and PDFs online. With MecSimCalc, it is now possible to share tools easier and run calculations faster than ever before.</p><p>This blog post is dedicated to Pharmacy tools that we have converted from PDF files into interactive online tools.</p><table><thead><tr><th>Tool</th><th>Source</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/0233855/diabetes_risk" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Diabetes Risk</a></td><td><a href="https://health.canada.ca/apps/canrisk-standalone/pdf/canrisk-en.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Health Canada</a></td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/8086574/body_surface_area_bsa" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Body Surface Area (BSA)</a></td><td><a href="https://www.pharmacists.ca/cpha-ca/assets/File/education-practice-resources/CalcAndDosing_EN_26Feb08.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pharmacists.ca</a></td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/5081549/body_surface_area_in_infants_children_or_adults" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Body Surface Area in Infants, Children or Adults</a></td><td><a href="https://www.pharmacists.ca/cpha-ca/assets/File/education-practice-resources/CalcAndDosing_EN_26Feb08.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pharmacists.ca</a></td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/5519816/ideal_body_weight_ibw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Ideal Body Weight (IBW)</a></td><td><a href="https://www.pharmacists.ca/cpha-ca/assets/File/education-practice-resources/CalcAndDosing_EN_26Feb08.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pharmacists.ca</a></td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/7850429/adjusted_body_weight_abw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Adjusted Body Weight (ABW)</a></td><td><a href="https://www.pharmacists.ca/cpha-ca/assets/File/education-practice-resources/CalcAndDosing_EN_26Feb08.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pharmacists.ca</a></td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/8292339/creatinine_clearance_cl_cr" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Creatinine Clearance (ClCr)</a></td><td><a href="https://www.pharmacists.ca/cpha-ca/assets/File/education-practice-resources/CalcAndDosing_EN_26Feb08.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pharmacists.ca</a></td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/9081445/framingham_risk_score_frs" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Framingham Risk Score (FRS)</a></td><td><a href="https://ccs.ca/app/uploads/2020/12/FRS_eng_2017_fnl_greyscale.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Canadian Cardiovascular Society</a></td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/0114458/ukpds_cardiac_risk_calculator" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">UKPDS Cardiac Risk Calculator</a></td><td><a href="https://www.mdapp.co/ukpds-cardiac-risk-calculator-215/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MDApp</a></td></tr></tbody></table>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Calculators</category>
            <category>Pharmacy</category>
            <category>Medicine</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[CSA S16-19 CivE Calculators]]></title>
            <link>https://docs.mecsimcalc.com/blog/csa-calculators-2022</link>
            <guid>csa-calculators-2022</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jun 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[I’ve spent the last month creating apps for the purpose of designing flexural members, compression members, tension members, and beam-columns in accordance with CSA S16-19.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’ve spent the last month creating apps for the purpose of designing flexural members, compression members, tension members, and beam-columns in accordance with CSA S16-19.</p><p>First, I had to learn Python. I took a 12-hour beginners course which was sufficient for learning the basics to Python, however not specific enough to be able to code the apps and get them to function as desired. Luckily, there are plenty of resources online and through watching YouTube tutorials, I was able to code the apps. Overall, learning python required lots of trial and error but was overall a smooth process due to the available resources.</p><p>I also had a very good experience using MecSimCalc as I found it incredibly easy to use and efficient, and it did not take long to adjust to.</p><p>Five applications have been created for design calculations in accordance with CSA S16-19. All applications require an input of the Cross Section, Yield Strength, and Unbraced Length of the member. The applications and their capabilities are presented below.</p><table><thead><tr><th>Calculator</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/4389397/design_of_flexural_members_with_w_section_csa_s_16_19" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Design of Flexural Members with W-Section</a></td><td>This application computes the Section Class, Plastic or Yield Flexural Moment, Factored Flexural Moment Resistance, and Factored Shear Resistance of W-Sections under uniformly distributed load. Along with the mentioned inputs, there is also a lateral support option. If the beam is laterally unsupported, the Equivalent Moment Factor and Critical Elastic Flexural Moment are also computed for the purpose of calculating the Factored Moment Resistance.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/7445336/design_of_compression_members_in_accordance_with_csa_s_16_19" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Design of Compression Members</a></td><td>This application checks the Width-to-Thickness Ratio, Slenderness, and computes the Factored Compression Resistance for W-Sections and HSS. Along with the general inputs for the CSA apps, there is also the option of support conditions, which is used to determine the Effective Length Factor in the Factored Compression Resistance calculations. If the compression member does not pass the Width-to-Thickness Ratio Check, the app stops there as the predicted resistance cannot actually be reached.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/0029258/design_of_tension_members_in_accordance_with_csa_s_16_19" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Design of Tension Members</a></td><td>This application calculates the Factored Tensile Resistance based on gross section yielding and performs a Serviceability Limit State (SLS) vibration check for W-Sections and HSS.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/3708352/w_shaped_beam_columns_under_major_axis_bending_csa_s_16_19" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">W-Section Beam-Columns under Major Axis Bending</a></td><td>This application performs the four limit state checks for Beam-Columns with W-Sections under major axis bending. Along with the general inputs, the app requires the user to input the Factored Compression Load, Smaller End Factored Moment, Larger End Factored Moment, Frame Type, and Moment Distribution. The four limit states that are checked are: Cross-Sectional Strength, Overall Member Strength, Lateral-Torsional Buckling Strength, and Moment Check.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/6568576/w_shaped_beam_columns_under_biaxial_bending_csa_s_16_19" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">W-Section Beam-Columns under Biaxial Bending</a></td><td>This application performs the four limit state checks for Beam-Columns with W-Sections under biaxial bending. The inputs and outputs are similar to the app for Beam-Columns under major axis bending.</td></tr></tbody></table>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Calculators</category>
            <category>Civil Engineering</category>
            <category>Engineering</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Starter Calculators]]></title>
            <link>https://docs.mecsimcalc.com/blog/starter-calculators-2021</link>
            <guid>starter-calculators-2021</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 17 Apr 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[The following are free-to-use calculators developed by researchers at the University of Alberta for a variety of disciplines.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The following are free-to-use calculators developed by researchers at the University of Alberta for a variety of disciplines.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="civil-engineering">Civil Engineering<a class="hash-link" href="#civil-engineering" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><table><thead><tr><th>App</th><th>Category</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/8201998/csa_s_16_1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">CSA S16-1</a></td><td>Structural Engineering</td><td>An application to determine class, moments and maximum shear of W section Steel beams.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/0595262/csa_s_16_2" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">CSA S16-2</a></td><td>Structural Engineering</td><td>Gives all beams with specified input</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/0935172/csa_s_16_tension_member" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">CSA S16 Tension Member</a></td><td>Structural Engineering</td><td>CSA S16 Tension Member</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/0201297/csa_s_16_compression_member" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">CSA S16 Compression Member</a></td><td>Structural Engineering</td><td>CSA S16 Compression Member</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/9717102/csa_s_16_flexure" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">CSA S16 Flexure</a></td><td>Structural Engineering</td><td>CSA S16 Flexure</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/6888704/strain_demand_in_pipes_subjected_to_ground_movement" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Strain Demand in Pipes Subjected to Ground Movement</a></td><td>Pipeline Engineering</td><td>This page analyzes the response of the pipe to ground movements induced by geotechnical activities, e.g., ground heave and subsidence, slope instability, landslides, liquefaction-induced action, and tectonic faults.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/4446725/stress_design_of_straight_pipe_according_to_csa_z_662_19" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Stress Design of Straight Pipe According to CSA Z662.19</a></td><td>Pipeline Engineering</td><td>CSA Z662.19 provides equations limiting the circumferential and longitudinal stresses in steel pipelines. Given the pipe properties and field conditions, this page performs the required checks according to sections 4.3.5.1, 4.7, and 4.8.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/9389449/stress_strain_curve_of_steel_materials" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Stress Strain Curve of Steel Materials</a></td><td>Pipeline Engineering</td><td>This page calculates converts the Engineering stress-strain curve to true stress-strain curve using the well known conversion equations. The page outputs the stress-plastic strain data required by some finite element analysis software and provides the best-fit Ramberg-Osgood approximation to the given data.</td></tr></tbody></table><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="electrical-engineering">Electrical Engineering<a class="hash-link" href="#electrical-engineering" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><table><thead><tr><th>App</th><th>Category</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/5558606/processor_comparison" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Processor Comparison</a></td><td>Hardware Engineering</td><td>Compares two processors by utilizing benchmark times for different programs.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/8483456/discrete_signals_difference_equations" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Discrete Signals Difference Equations</a></td><td>Signal Processing</td><td>An application to determine values of a difference equation. Assumptions are sets the x(n)=δ(n) (the impulse function) and y(n)=0 for n&lt;0. Make sure n is greater than the size of Y coefficients.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/9697406/convolution" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Convolution</a></td><td>Signal Processing</td><td>An application to determine x<!-- -->[n]<!-- -->*<!-- -->h<!-- -->[n]<!-- --> = y<!-- -->[n]<!-- -->. The input contains the n index of each coefficient, such as the first element is n = 0 for the x function.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/1085971/circular_convolution" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Circular Convolution</a></td><td>Signal Processing</td><td>An application to determine the circular convolution of 2 functions.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/5513818/floating_point_binary_numbers" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Floating point binary numbers</a></td><td>Binary</td><td>Floating point numbers can be represented using IEEE 754 in binary. This system uses one sign bit, then a set number of exponent (k) bits and finally, fraction (n) bits. Depending on the number of these bits, the representations of numbers change as well. This calculator is made with the intention of getting the largest floating point number possible as well as the largest integer. There are restrictions on the number of bits that can be checked, due to an overflow possibility in python.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/0378917/hard_disk_drive_hdd_reading_a_file" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Hard Disk Drive (HDD) Reading a File</a></td><td>Hardware Engineering</td><td>Best and random cases of the time an HDD will take to read over a file. Assumes both block size and sector size are the same</td></tr></tbody></table><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="chemistry">Chemistry<a class="hash-link" href="#chemistry" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><table><thead><tr><th>App</th><th>Category</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/0663779/thermo_question_type_1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Thermo Question Type 1</a></td><td>Thermodynamics</td><td>An application to determine quality given certain knowns and unknowns. Known variable values must correspond to Thermo tables.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/1903331/thermo_question_type_2" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Thermo Question Type 2</a></td><td>Thermodynamics</td><td>An application to determine particular unknown given certain knowns. Known variable values must correspond to Thermo tables.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/2584336/thermo_question_type_1_b" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Thermo Question Type 1b</a></td><td>Thermodynamics</td><td>An application to determine a specific value given certain knowns and unknowns. Known variable values must correspond to Thermo tables.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/3069689/diagrams" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Diagrams</a></td><td>Thermodynamics</td><td>An application to graph Pv and Tv graphs.</td></tr></tbody></table><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="physics">Physics<a class="hash-link" href="#physics" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><table><thead><tr><th>App</th><th>Category</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/3152375/thin_lens_equation" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Thin Lens Equation</a></td><td>Optics</td><td>Knowing the distance an object is from a lens, we can determine the focal length and the magnification.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/9676607/thin_compound_lens_equation" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Thin Compound Lens Equation</a></td><td>Optics</td><td>We can find combined focal length of two lens. If d is input as being greater than f_1, then it will be assumed that d is 0.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/6017792/lensmaker_equation" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Lensmaker Equation</a></td><td>Optics</td><td>The lens maker equation can be used to find both the Power and focal length of a thick lens and a thin lens if the thickness tends to 0.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/1227912/snells_law" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Snell's Law</a></td><td>Optics</td><td>This application will derive the angle of refraction using Snell's Law.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/5545394/coulombs_law" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Coulomb's Law</a></td><td>Electrostatic</td><td>Coulomb's Law with three point charges</td></tr></tbody></table><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="business-and-finance">Business and Finance<a class="hash-link" href="#business-and-finance" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><table><thead><tr><th>App</th><th>Category</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/6285257/antique_lamps" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Antique Lamps</a></td><td>Max Profit Estimation</td><td>An application to maximize profits, with the given types of lamps, bass, and platinum. Maximize, has 2 inputs with their coefficients. Assembly has 3 inputs, each being its respective coefficients, and Max demand has 1 input. The coefficients are aB+ bP = cC where B is brass, P is platinum, and C is the constant, with the input <!-- -->[a,b,c]<!-- -->. The inputs are interpreted into functions where it is drawn on the graph. There will be a feasible region where all boundaries will be satisfied. The program then picks all the intersections within the feasible region(note that some points will not be accounted for). The output just gives the profits given at that point on the graph.</td></tr><tr><td><a href="https://mecsimcalc.com/app/4532115/cattle_profit" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Cattle Profit</a></td><td>Max Profit Estimation</td><td>An application to maximize profits (only gives boundaries), the first table consists of the first element being the regular, and the 2nd being the premium. The second table consists of the first element being alfalfa and the second being barley. This can also be translated such as the required material for a toy car to be inputted, but in this case it is just using cattle profit as the output. The program basically just gives the boundaries and conditions of what to expect before proceeding onto the next step.</td></tr></tbody></table>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Calculators</category>
            <category>Engineering</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Welcome to MecSimCalc]]></title>
            <link>https://docs.mecsimcalc.com/blog/welcome</link>
            <guid>welcome</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Welcome to our newly released MecSimCalc platform for creating and sharing computational tools on the web. With a few very simple steps, educators and professionals can create interactive web applications for their students or clients.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to our newly released <strong>MecSimCalc</strong> platform for <strong>creating</strong> and <strong>sharing</strong> computational tools on the web. With a few very simple steps, educators and professionals can create interactive web applications for their students or clients.</p><p><strong>MecSimCalc</strong> has been a concept in my head since I joined the Engineering Faculty at the University of Alberta in 2007. At the time, I was looking for an easy way to create interactive web examples for my students to help them visualize different Mathematical and Engineering concepts. Throughout the years, I experimented with <a href="https://www.wolfram.com/products/webmathematica/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">webMathematica</a> and <a href="https://www.javascript.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">javascripts</a>. However, dealing with web infrastructure has always been a struggle. I still remember the agony of trying to switch my whole website from traditional HTTP to HTTPS or the yearly agony of renewing the licenses of the different components that I was using. Throughout the years, my experience has shaped my vision for creating <strong>MecSimCalc</strong> as a platform that frees the developer from all the ever changing web architecture to allow them to focus on their application.</p><p><strong>MecSimCalc</strong> is a simple, yet extremely powerful platform that has applications in a large array of fields. Here is an example in <a href="https://www.mecsimcalc.com/app/7188609/diabetes_risk" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Medicine</a>, by answering a simple questionnaire, a visitor to the app can identify their diabetes risk. The app was created based on an algorithm published on a <a href="https://www.healthycanadians.gc.ca/en/canrisk" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Canadian government website</a>. For University Mathematics <a href="https://www.mecsimcalc.com/app/4730621/numerical_integration" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Education</a>, a student can enter any functional expression and the limits of an integral while the interactive app would calculate the numerical integral and would provide a plot, powered by <code>matplotlib</code> for visual illustration of the example.</p><p>We created <strong>MecSimCalc</strong> for professionals in engineering and finance. Consider the <a href="https://www.mecsimcalc.com/app/3333910/mortgage_calculator" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">app</a> that can be distributed by a mortgage specialist to his or her clients to help them identify the price of the house that matches their finances. Or consider the <a href="https://www.mecsimcalc.com/app/8106967/cor_las_model" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Engineering app</a> that uses the <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/309917227_Review_of_Engineering_Fracture_Mechanics_Model_for_Pipeline_Applications" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">CorLAS</a> algorithm to calculate the failure pressure of pipelines with longitudinal crack like features. While these apps are currently publicly available, we can work with any professionals to help them build and share their specific applications only with their clients.</p><p>I welcome all our visitors to <a href="https://www.mecsimcalc.com/explore" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">explore</a> the different applications that have been created using <strong>MecSimCalc</strong>.</p><p>We also invite all professionals, scientists, and educators who would like to publicly or privately publish their lively algorithms to try out our <strong>free</strong> platform. We promise to keep it free for any publicly available applications. We are also happy to work with any professionals wishing to use <strong>MecSimCalc</strong> for their enterprise applications.</p><p>Please send us any suggestions, questions, or inquiries to <a href="mailto:info@mecsimcalc.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">info@mecsimcalc.com</a></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>MecSimCalc</category>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>